// File: infectionControlQuestions.js
let infectionControlQuestions = [
  {
    question: "After accepting employment you opt not to receive a hepatitis B vaccination and have signed a waiver to this effect. You have the right to:",
    answers: ["Change your mind and have the vaccination at your own expense",
              "Change your mind and the employer is required to provide the vaccination",
              "Demand periodic blood tests to ensure noninvasion of the hepatitis B virus in your body",
              "Sue the employer if you contact hepatitis B"],
    correct: 1,
    category: "Infection Control",
    rationale: "In accordance with the OSHA Bloodborne Pathogens Standard, an employee who initially declines the vaccination may at a later date, while still covered under the standard, decide to accept the offer. The employer must make the vaccine available at no charge at that time."
  },



{
  question: "For a disease transmission to take place, there must be a pathogen present in sufficient quantity, a reservoir for microorganisms, a mode of transmission, and:",
  answers: ["a bloodborne pathogen",
            "a susceptible individual",
            "a contaminated surface",
            "an unsterile instrument"],
  correct: 1,
  category: "Infection Control",
  rationale: "Pathogenic microorganisms will be much less likely to cause an infection in an individual who is not susceptible to infection, because of the individual's immune function and immunization against vaccine preventable diseases."
},


{
  question: "The infection that is not spread by airborne transmission is:",
  answers: ["chickenpox",
            "measles",
            "tuberculosis",
            "hepatitis C"],
  correct: 3,
  category: "Infection Control",
  rationale: "Hepatitis C is transmitted by blood and blood products. Chickenpox, measles, and tuberculosis are all spread by droplet infection."
},



{
  question: "Bloodborne transmission of certain viruses, such as human immunodeficiency virus (HIV), can occur through cuts, punctures, and:",
  answers: ["breathing contaminated aerosol",
            "spatter of blood onto mucous membranes",
            "wearing contaminated clothing",
            "reusing face masks"],
  correct: 1,
  category: "Infection Control",
  rationale: "Mucous membranes are very thin tissues with many tiny blood vessels. HIV and other pathogens can pass through these membranes and into the bloodstream, causing infections."
},



{
  question: "An unvaccinated dental healthcare worker is at greatest risk of exposure to which microorganism during dental treatment procedures?",
  answers: ["hepatitis A",
            "hepatitis B",
            "hepatitis C",
            "hepatitis D"],
  correct: 1,
  category: "Infection Control",
  rationale: "Hepatitis B poses the greatest risk because it is easily transmitted during dental procedures, requiring less virus and smaller amounts of blood to cause an infection than hepatitis C. Hepatitis D infections take place only in persons infected with hepatitis B. Hepatitis A is a foodborne and waterborne virus and therefore is not an occupational risk."
},


{
  question: "Which of the following is not a protocol for standard precautions?",
  answers: ["wearing appropriate personal protective equipment",
            "relying on the patient's health history as an indication of risk",
            "using a preprocedural mouth rinse on all patients",
            "using dental dam isolation whenever possible"],
  correct: 1,
  category: "Infection Control",
  rationale: "Health histories are not a reliable resource for determining the potential infectivity of a patient. Therefore, standard precautions dictate that every patient should be treated as an infection risk and the recommended precautions should be followed, despite indications on the medical history."
},


  {
    question: "Which is a recommended method used to prevent surface contamination?",
    answers: ["Use a surface barrier.",
              "Wipe the surface with alcohol.",
              "Use an intermediate level disinfectant.",
              "Use a high level disinfectant."],
    correct: 0,
    category: "Infection Control",
    rationale: "The use of a surface barrier made of fluid resistant material is recommended. The use of alcohol is not acceptable by any of the agencies that are concerned with dental office treatment areas. The other two answers are not necessary when the surface barrier is used unless there is spatter evident."
  },
  {
    question: "Which is an unsafe practice in recapping of a needle?",
    answers: ["one handed scoop method",
              "a mechanical device specifically designed to hold the needle for recapping",
              "any safety feature that is fixed, provides a barrier between the assistant's hands and the needle after use, and allows the assistant's hands to remain behind the needle",
              "a two handed scoop method for maximal control"],
    correct: 3,
    category: "Infection Control",
    rationale: "The dental assistant must never use a two handed scoop method; it is potentially dangerous because the assistant could slip and cause a needle puncture."
  },
  {
    question: "Patients who are infected with HIV or AIDS are:",
    answers: ["a high risk to dental healthcare workers during treatment",
              "best referred to a specialist for treatment in a hospital setting",
              "protected from discrimination by the Americans with Disabilities Act",
              "taking medications that may contraindicate dental treatment"],
    correct: 2,
    category: "Infection Control",
    rationale: "The Americans with Disabilities Act (ADA) protects individuals with certain medical conditions, including human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) or acquired immunodeficiency syndrome (AIDS), from discrimination in the provision of services. A dental practice cannot deny treatment to an HIV or AIDS patient or refer him or her to a specialist only on the basis of this infection."
  },
  {
    question: "A dental assistant has completed the series of injections for hepatitis B vaccination. The next step is to:",
    answers: ["provide a copy of the vaccine record for his or her employer",
              "get a blood test for HBV antibodies",
              "follow up in 5 years with a booster injection",
              "get reimbursed by his or her employer for the cost of the injections"],
    correct: 1,
    category: "Infection Control",
    rationale: "A titer test for hepatitis B virus (HBV) antibodies is recommended 1–2 months after the final injection. If antibodies are not detectable, a medical care provider may recommend another series of injections."
  },
  {
    question: "If patients indicate on their health history that they have active tuberculosis, this means that:",
    answers: ["they are taking antibiotics, and it is safe to treat them in the dental office",
              "they should not have elective treatment performed in the dental office",
              "it is safe to treat them if they have been on antibiotics for 6 months",
              "it is safe to treat them if the dental team wears N95 respirators"],
    correct: 1,
    category: "Infection Control",
    rationale: "Patients with active tuberculosis infections should not receive elective treatment (e.g., cleanings, routine fillings) because of the risk of exposing the dental team from the aerosol created during treatment. Only emergency treatment should be provided, and the dentist and assistant must wear N95 respirators. Patients' status with regard to tuberculosis should always be confirmed by their treating physicians."
  },
  {
    question: "Which type of gloves does the CDC recommend for surgical procedures?",
    answers: ["latex",
              "nonlatex",
              "sterile",
              "nitrile"],
    correct: 2,
    category: "Infection Control",
    rationale: "Sterile surgical gloves are recommended by the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC) for all surgical procedures to protect the patient from potential exposure to microorganisms that may potentially contaminate examination gloves."
  },
  {
    question: "How much time should a surgical hand scrub take the dental assistant to perform?",
    answers: ["15–20 seconds",
              "30–60 seconds",
              "1–2 minutes",
              "2–6 minutes"],
    correct: 3,
    category: "Infection Control",
    rationale: "The time recommended by the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC) for a surgical hand scrub is 2–6 minutes, and the hand scrub should include washing hands, between fingers, wrists, and forearms and cleaning underneath fingernails."
  },
  {
    question: "When a dental assistant is cleaning instruments, what type(s) of personal protective equipment should be worn?",
    answers: ["goggles or full face shield, examination gloves, and protective gown",
              "goggles or full face shield, utility gloves, and protective gown",
              "goggles or full face shield, examination gloves, face mask, and protective gown",
              "goggles or full face shield, utility gloves, face mask, and protective gown"],
    correct: 3,
    category: "Infection Control",
    rationale: "According to the Occupational Safety and Health Administration (OSHA) Bloodborne Pathogens Standard, the appropriate personal protective equipment (PPE) for cleaning instruments includes safety glasses, puncture resistant utility gloves, a face mask, and protective clothing, to protect the dental assistant from spatter and splash of debris and from punctures to the hands."
  },
  {
    question: "Disposable devices, such as saliva ejector tips, can be reused if they are:",
    answers: ["cleaned in an ultrasonic cleaner and heat sterilized",
              "cleaned and placed in a liquid chemical sterilant",
              "not exposed to blood during treatment",
              "not to be reused, as they are single use devices"],
    correct: 3,
    category: "Infection Control",
    rationale: "Disposable devices should be used on only one patient and never reused."
  },
  {
    question: "The following are all true of disposable devices except that they:",
    answers: ["reduce the amount of waste produced by a dental practice",
              "can be disposed of in the regular office trash",
              "help to reduce transfer of microorganisms from one patient to another",
              "can help to save cleanup and instrument processing time"],
    correct: 1,
    category: "Infection Control",
    rationale: "Unfortunately, disposing of some products after each use in dentistry contributes to the waste generated by the dental practice. But this is, in most cases, outweighed by the patient safety that is gained by using disposable devices."
  },


  {
    question: "Even though the dental laboratory disinfects impressions and appliances that are received from the dental office, the responsibility of the dental office is to:",
    answers: ["label the item in a biohazard bag for transport to the laboratory",
              "disinfect every item that is sent to the laboratory",
              "consult with laboratory technicians about their preferences",
              "advise the laboratory that the laboratory is responsible for disinfecting the items"],
    correct: 1,
    category: "Infection Control",
    rationale: "The Occupational Safety and Health Administration (OSHA) Bloodborne Pathogens Standard requires dental practices to disinfect all items before they are sent from the treatment facility to the dental laboratory. Many laboratories also disinfect the items when they receive them, because they are not sure if this procedure has been performed, and they are protecting their personnel."
  },
  {
    question: "Whenever there is potential for spatter or splash of blood or saliva during dental treatment, the clinical team members must wear which of the following personal protective equipment?",
    answers: ["gloves, face masks, and goggles or full face shields",
              "gloves, face masks goggles or full face shields, and protective gowns",
              "face masks and goggles or full face shields",
              "face masks, goggles or full face shields, and protective gowns"],
    correct: 1,
    category: "Infection Control",
    rationale: "The Occupational Safety and Health Administration (OSHA) Bloodborne Pathogens Standard requires the use of safety glasses, face masks, gloves, and protective clothing whenever there is potential for exposure to blood or other potentially infectious materials from spatter or splash. Examples would be the use of an air/water syringe, high speed handpiece, or ultrasonic scaler."
  },
  {
    question: "Alcohol hand rubs are most effective in dental settings when:",
    answers: ["soap and hot water are not available for the dental assistant",
              "there is no debris on the hands of the dental assistant",
              "antimicrobial soap is irritating to the skin",
              "the alcohol product used is at least 60% ethyl alcohol"],
    correct: 1,
    category: "Infection Control",
    rationale: "Alcohol hand rubs are not good cleaners; therefore, if there is debris on the hands of the dental assistant, a soap and water hand wash should be performed. Although the Food and Drug Administration (FDA) requires alcohol hand rubs to be at least 60% alcohol, recent studies show that higher alcohol contents are more effective at sanitizing the hands of healthcare personnel."
  },
  {
    question: "Artificial nails are not recommended in dental settings because they:",
    answers: ["can puncture examination gloves and pose a risk to the dental assistant",
              "have been linked to disease transmission in healthcare settings",
              "do not promote a professional appearance for the dental assistant",
              "can interfere with handwashing procedures"],
    correct: 1,
    category: "Infection Control",
    rationale: "A number of cases of bacterial infections spread from the fingernails of healthcare workers have been documented. The Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC) recommends that artificial nails should not be worn in clinical settings and that natural nails should be short, to facilitate cleaning and reduce the surface area where microorganisms may accumulate."
  },
  {
    question: "Hand lotions with petroleum  or oil based ingredients should not be used in a dental office because these products can:",
    answers: ["make the hand slippery and cause puncture injuries",
              "cause the gloves to be more difficult to put on and take off",
              "weaken the glove material, especially latex",
              "cause the gloves to become contaminated"],
    correct: 2,
    category: "Infection Control",
    rationale: "Numerous studies have demonstrated that petroleum or oils can weaken or break down glove material, especially latex, which can pose an infection risk to healthcare workers."
  },
  {
    question: "When patient treatment is completed under standard precautions, the dental assistant should:",
    answers: ["remove and dispose of examination gloves",
              "remove and dispose of gloves and then the face mask",
              "remove and dispose of gloves and then face mask and wash hands",
              "remove and dispose of gloves, wash hands, and remove and dispose of face mask"],
    correct: 3,
    category: "Infection Control",
    rationale: "After patient treatment, the dental assistant should remove and dispose of examination gloves and then the face mask, and then wash hands before leaving the treatment room."
  },
  {
    question: "The following are true of chin length face shields, except that they:",
    answers: ["can be used in place of safety glasses or goggles",
              "can be used in place of safety glasses and face masks",
              "protect from large amounts of debris or spatter, such as in surgical procedures",
              "help to keep face masks dry during procedures"],
    correct: 1,
    category: "Infection Control",
    rationale: "Chin length face shields may be used in place of safety glasses, but they do not provide respiratory protection, and therefore they cannot be used in place of face masks. A mask must be worn underneath a face shield."
  },
  {
    question: "If a glove tears during patient treatment, the dental assistant should:",
    answers: ["place another glove on top of the torn glove",
              "remove the gloves, wash hands, and don a new pair of gloves",
              "report to the OSHA manager that there has been an exposure incident",
              "continue with the procedure if the doctor says that it is acceptable"],
    correct: 1,
    category: "Infection Control",
    rationale: "The dental assistant should immediately remove the torn glove, wash hands to remove any potential contamination, and put on a new pair of gloves."
  },
  {
    question: "When leaving the dental office at night, what should the dental assistant do with his or her laboratory coat worn while treating patients?",
    answers: ["Take it off at the office and take it home to be laundered.",
              "Take it off at the office, and place it in a leakproof bag to take home to be laundered.",
              "Place it in a container with a biohazard label for laundry in the office.",
              "Take it home and launder it separately from other clothing."],
    correct: 2,
    category: "Infection Control",
    rationale: "Dental healthcare personnel are not allowed to wear or take contaminated clothing home for laundering. If the office has in house laundry facilities, the contaminated clothing should be placed in a container with a biohazard label or placed directly into the washer. An outside laundry service can also be used."
  },
  {
    question: "What type of soap is not acceptable for handwashing in dental care settings?",
    answers: ["plain liquid soap",
              "antimicrobial bar soap",
              "antimicrobial liquid soap",
              "antimicrobial foam soap"],
    correct: 1,
    category: "Infection Control",
    rationale: "Bar soap is never acceptable in healthcare settings, because it can serve as a reservoir for microorganisms and cannot be disinfected."
  },


  {
    question: "What are the steps in the handwashing process (in order)?",
    answers: ["Wet hands with water, apply soap, rub hands for 15 seconds, rinse hands.",
              "Wet hands with water, apply soap, rub hands for 15 seconds, rinse and dry hands.",
              "Apply soap, add water, rub hands for 15 seconds, rinse and dry hands.",
              "Apply soap, add water, rub hands for 15 seconds, rinse hands."],
    correct: 1,
    category: "Infection Control",
    rationale: "Hands should be wet first before the application of soap. A 15 second lathering is recommended for nonsurgical handwashing, and hands should always be rinsed and dried to prevent irritation from soap and to facilitate donning gloves."
  },
  {
    question: "What types of gloves can be washed and reused in dentistry?",
    answers: ["nitrile examination gloves",
              "nitrile utility gloves",
              "synthetic gloves",
              "vinyl gloves"],
    correct: 1,
    category: "Infection Control",
    rationale: "Only utility gloves may be washed and reused. Examination gloves may be used only once. Nitrile examination gloves are not equivalent to utility gloves, because they are not puncture or chemical resistant."
  },
  {
    question: "When does a laboratory coat or protective gown need to be changed under standard precautions?",
    answers: ["after each patient",
              "at the end of every day",
              "once a week when the laundry service picks up",
              "if it becomes visibly soiled with blood"],
    correct: 3,
    category: "Infection Control",
    rationale: "The Occupational Safety and Health Administration (OSHA) Bloodborne Pathogens Standard requires protective clothing to be changed if it becomes visibly soiled with blood, to prevent cross contamination."
  },
  {
    question: "Which of the following is an indirect contact mode of disease transmission?",
    answers: ["touching soft tissue or teeth in a patient's mouth",
              "puncture from a contaminated anesthetic needle",
              "spatter droplets of a patient's oral fluids contacting the eye",
              "inhalation of droplet nuclei in dental aerosols"],
    correct: 2,
    category: "Infection Control",
    rationale: "Indirect contact involves a contaminated intermediate object between the source and the recipient such as a needle, hands, instrument, or operatory surface. Direct contact is directly touching contaminants. Droplet infection involves contact with the larger respiratory spatter droplets. Airborne infection involves inhalation of small aerosol respiratory particles called droplet nuclei."
  },
  {
    question: "Which of the following is a direct contact mode of disease transmission?",
    answers: ["touching soft tissue or teeth in a patient's mouth",
              "puncture from a contaminated anesthetic needle",
              "spatter droplets of a patient's oral fluids contacting the eye",
              "inhalation of droplet nuclei in dental aerosols"],
    correct: 0,
    category: "Infection Control",
    rationale: "Direct contact involves directly touching contaminated material such as working on a patient while not wearing gloves. Indirect contact involves contamination of an intermediate object that transfers the contamination to another person or surface. Droplet infection involves contact with the larger respiratory spatter droplets. Airborne infection involves inhalation of small aerosol respiratory particles called droplet nuclei."
  },
  {
    question: "Droplet infection can occur through exposure to aerosol and spatter during dental procedures and also through:",
    answers: ["contact with patient's tissues",
              "coughing and sneezing",
              "contact with environmental surfaces",
              "handling contaminated instruments"],
    correct: 1,
    category: "Infection Control",
    rationale: "Coughing and sneezing can cause the release of bacteria and viruses from an infected individual that can be inhaled by another individual."
  },
  {
    question: "According to the CDC, instruments should be packaged before sterilization, unless they will be:",
    answers: ["stored in closed drawers or cabinets",
              "placed into pouches immediately after sterilization",
              "used immediately after they have been sterilized",
              "placed inside sealed containers after sterilization"],
    correct: 2,
    category: "Infection Control",
    rationale: "If instruments are taken directly from the sterilizer to the treatment room for use, it is appropriate to place them unpackaged in the sterilizer. In all other situations, the instruments must be packaged to protect them from potential contamination during storage. When instruments are exposed to the environment, they are no longer considered to be sterile."
  },
  {
    question: "When a used needle is removed from a syringe during treatment, it should be placed:",
    answers: ["on the side of the instrument tray away from other instruments",
              "in a sharps container in the treatment room",
              "in a plastic cup to isolate it from other instruments",
              "in a red bag used for biohazardous waste"],
    correct: 1,
    category: "Infection Control",
    rationale: "A contaminated needle or other disposable sharp item should be placed immediately into a sharps container in the treatment area."
  },
  {
    question: "Sharps containers should be replaced when:",
    answers: ["the contents reach the top of the container",
              "the contents reach the fill line on the container",
              "the contents begin to overflow the container",
              "new containers are purchased"],
    correct: 1,
    category: "Infection Control",
    rationale: "Each sharps container is clearly marked with a fill line, and the container should be replaced when the contents reach that line. This is to prevent any items from overflowing and preventing the container from being closed for disposal. Sharps containers should never be opened to access the contents and should never be allowed to be overfilled. Some states, however, require replacement of sharps containers after a specified period of time, whether or not the contents have reached the fill line."
  },

  {
    question: "What type of water or irrigant should be used during surgical procedures?",
    answers: [
      "sterile water or saline",
      "distilled water",
      "diluted chlorhexidine",
      "treated water from the dental unit"
    ],
    correct: 0,
    category: "Infection Control",
    rationale: "The Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC) recommends that only sterile water or saline be used for irrigation during surgical procedures to prevent infections at the surgical site from contaminated water. In addition, sterile water and saline are not irritating to the tissues, as other skin antiseptics, such as chlorhexidine, might be."
  },
  {
    question: "If the dental assistant suspects that the sterility of a multiple dose medication vial has been compromised, he or she should:",
    answers: [
      "clean the access diaphragm with isopropyl alcohol",
      "ensure that a sterile needle is used to draw up the medication",
      "discard the vial in an appropriate container",
      "record the incident in the medication log"
    ],
    correct: 2,
    category: "Infection Control",
    rationale: "If a drug vial becomes contaminated or contamination is suspected, it should not be used. The vial should be disposed of in an appropriate container. Contaminated drug vials have been associated with hepatitis C infections in healthcare facilities."
  },
  {
    question: "Which of the following is (are) means by which chemicals can enter the human body?",
    answers: [
      "inhalation",
      "absorption through the skin",
      "eating or swallowing them",
      "all of the above"
    ],
    correct: 3,
    category: "Infection Control",
    rationale: "Chemicals are absorbed into the body in a variety of ways. This is why the various types of personal protective equipment are necessary (e.g., masks, gloves, and protective eyewear)."
  },
  {
    question: "What should be done to instrument packages just before they are opened for use on the patient?",
    answers: [
      "Check them for tears or punctures.",
      "Rinse them off with clean or sterile water.",
      "Check the dates on the packages.",
      "Disinfect them by the spray wipe spray process."
    ],
    correct: 0,
    category: "Infection Control",
    rationale: "If packaging material is torn, punctured, or wet, the instruments need to be recleaned, repackaged, and resterilized. Dating of packages should occur before they are placed in the sterilizer. Packages should never get wet, because this causes a drawing through of any microbes on the package surface."
  },
  {
    question: "Using an ultrasonic cleaning basket reduces the direct handling of instruments, allows for easy placement into and removal from the cleaning solution, facilitates rinsing of the cleaned instruments, and:",
    answers: [
      "raises the instruments off the bottom of the tank to provide optimal cleaning",
      "prevents corrosion of the instruments",
      "keeps the cleaning solution from splashing out of the tank",
      "eliminates the need for a tank cover"
    ],
    correct: 0,
    category: "Infection Control",
    rationale: "The best cleaning occurs toward the top of the cleaning solution, not on the bottom. The basket is not related to preventing corrosion or splashing or to using a cover."
  },
  {
    question: "The appropriate parameters for unsaturated chemical vapor sterilization are:",
    answers: [
      "15 minutes at 250°F",
      "20 minutes at 250°F",
      "15 minutes at 270°F",
      "20 minutes at 270°F"
    ],
    correct: 2,
    category: "Infection Control",
    rationale: "Twenty minutes at 270°F is the parameter for unsaturated chemical vapor sterilizers. The time does not include warmup, cooling, and drying time."
  },
  {
    question: "The appropriate parameters for static air dry heat sterilization of packaged items are:",
    answers: [
      "20 minutes at 300°F",
      "40 minutes at 350°F",
      "60 minutes at 300°F",
      "60 minutes at 320°F"
    ],
    correct: 3,
    category: "Infection Control",
    rationale: "The appropriate parameters are 60 minutes at 320°F. This does not include warmup or cooling time."
  },
  {
    question: "A key advantage of using an unsaturated chemical vapor sterilizer is that it:",
    answers: [
      "has a shorter cycle than a steam autoclave",
      "does not cause rust or corrosion like a steam autoclave",
      "can be used with cloth wraps",
      "does not damage plastic items"
    ],
    correct: 1,
    category: "Infection Control",
    rationale: "Unsaturated chemical vapor sterilization uses a solution that does not contain water, which is the agent that can rust or corrode instruments in a steam autoclave."
  },
  {
    question: "Flash sterilization can be achieved in a steam autoclave by:",
    answers: [
      "placing only unpackaged items in the sterilizer",
      "operating the sterilizer at a higher temperature",
      "using a shorter time and a higher temperature",
      "placing the item to be sterilized in a glass bead sterilizer"
    ],
    correct: 0,
    category: "Infection Control",
    rationale: "Although flash sterilization is not appropriate in all cases, it can be accomplished by using a shorter time and a higher temperature cycle in the autoclave."
  },
  {
    question: "To help prevent rust or corrosion of items in a steam autoclave, the instruments should be __________ before they are placed in the autoclave:",
    answers: [
      "dried",
      "cleaned",
      "packaged",
      "wrapped"
    ],
    correct: 0,
    category: "Infection Control",
    rationale: "Drying instruments helps to prevent rust and corrosion. In addition, excess moisture on the instruments that are placed in the sterilizer has been shown to interfere with the sterilization cycle."
  },

{
  question: "Instrument packs must always be allowed to dry before handling, because the wet paper may tear and the:",
  answers: [
    "paper may draw or 'wick' microorganisms into the package",
    "instruments may rust or corrode because of the wet packaging material",
    "process indicator may not change color until the packs are dry",
    "cutting edges on the instruments may become dull"
  ],
  correct: 1,
  category: "Infection Control",
  rationale: "Wet packaging material may draw contaminants in the air into the instrument package and contaminate the instruments."
},

{
  question: "A possible drawback to using an unsaturated chemical vapor sterilizer is that it can:",
  answers: [
    "cause rust or corrosion of dental instruments",
    "dull the cutting edges of dental instruments",
    "expose the dental team to the chemical vapor",
    "require biologic monitoring"
  ],
  correct: 2,
  category: "Infection Control",
  rationale: "Unsaturated chemical vapors should be used only in a well ventilated area, and the dental team must follow the manufacturers' guidelines for preventing environmental exposure to the sterilizing solution."
},

{
  question: "According to the CDC, immersion in a high level disinfectant/sterilant is not recommended for items that can withstand heat sterilization because:",
  answers: [
    "high level disinfectants/sterilants may damage metal items",
    "the process can take up to 12 hours, according to the manufacturer’s instructions",
    "the solution may be diluted by each addition of wet instruments",
    "high level disinfectant/sterilants cannot be monitored with a biologic indicator"
  ],
  correct: 3,
  category: "Infection Control",
  rationale: "Only items that are reusable and heat sensitive should be chemically sterilized, because spore testing of these solutions is not possible. Some sterilizing solutions have monitors for testing concentration, but they do not provide proof of sterilization."
},

{
  question: "OSHA requires infection control training records to be kept on file in a dental practice for:",
  answers: [
    "10 years",
    "5 years",
    "3 years",
    "7 years"
  ],
  correct: 2,
  category: "Infection Control",
  rationale: "Although it may be wise to always keep training records on file, the Occupational Safety and Health Administration (OSHA) Bloodborne Pathogens Standard requires the records to be kept for only 3 years."
},

{
  question: "Patient care items that penetrate soft tissue, such as scalers and curettes, have the highest risk of transmitting infection and are classified by the CDC as:",
  answers: [
    "noncritical",
    "semicritical",
    "critical",
    "reusable"
  ],
  correct: 2,
  category: "Infection Control",
  rationale: "These items are classified as critical items because they are most likely to be contaminated with blood."
},

{
  question: "The purpose of using a holding solution before instrument sterilization is to:",
  answers: [
    "disinfect the items, making them safer to handle",
    "prevent blood and debris from drying on the items",
    "prevent rust and corrosion on instruments",
    "eliminate the need for hand scrubbing of instruments"
  ],
  correct: 1, // assumes 0 based indexing
  category: "Infection Control",
  rationale: "If blood and debris are allowed to dry on instruments before cleaning, it is much harder to remove the blood and debris. Using a holding solution or placing the items in the ultrasonic cleaner immediately after use prevents this from happening. It is important to note that glutaraldehyde is not to be used as a holding solution, because it will fixate blood on instruments, making them harder to clean."
},

{
 question: "Devices used for instrument sterilization must be:",
  answers: [
    "able to achieve a temperature of 250°F",
    "able to achieve a temperature of 270°F",
    "cleared by the FDA as medical devices",
    "registered with the state dental board"
  ],
  correct: 2,
  category: "Infection Control",
  rationale: "Sterilizers and any other devices used for dental treatment must have a 510(k) clearance from the Food and Drug Administration (FDA), to prove their safety and efficacy."
},

{
  question: "What should be done to a blood spotted surface before disinfecting that surface?",
  answers: [
    "Nothing should be done.",
    "Wash it with a high level disinfectant/sterilant.",
    "Clean the surface with a cleaner or a disinfectant/cleaner.",
    "Completely dry the surface before disinfecting."
  ],
  correct: 2,
  category: "Infection Control",
  rationale: "Most disinfectants are to be used on a precleaned surface, particularly if blood is present. High level disinfectant/sterilants should never be used to wipe down a surface."
},

{
  question: "The CDC recommended method for decontaminating environmental surfaces is:",
  answers: [
    "wipe once to clean and disinfect",
    "wipe once after spraying",
    "clean first, then disinfect",
    "wipe with a high level disinfectant"
  ],
  correct: 2,
  category: "Infection Control",
  rationale: "In the 2003 Guidelines for Infection Control in Dental Health Care Settings, the CDC no longer recommended the spray wipe spray method of cleaning and disinfection. The guidelines now say to clean first, which can be accomplished with a wipe saturated with an intermediate level disinfectant, and then disinfect with a new disinfectant saturated wipe."
},

{
  question: "A disinfectant is best defined as:",
  answers: [
    "an antimicrobial handwashing agent",
    "a liquid sterilant used in special chemical vapor sterilizers",
    "an antimicrobial chemical use on inanimate surfaces to kill pathogenic microbes",
    "an agent used to sterilize surfaces contaminated with bacterial spores"
  ],
  correct: 2,
  category: "Infection Control",
  rationale: "Disinfectants are to be used only on inanimate surfaces to kill most microbes. They are not to be used as handwashing agents and they do not sterilize (kill all types of microbes)."
},

{
  question: "Dental treatment water that is unfiltered or untreated may be the source of pathogenic microorganisms, including:",
  answers: [
    "hepatitis A and E virus",
    "Legionella",
    "coronavirus",
    "Salmonella"
  ],
  correct: 1,
  category: "Infection Control",
  rationale: "Many researchers have isolated Legionella bacteria from dental treatment water, and Legionella has been isolated in dental practices, including an instance in Italy in 2012, where an elderly woman died from a Legionella infection that was traced to her dental office. Viruses, such as hepatitis A and E viruses, although waterborne, are not typically found in dental treatment water in the United States. Salmonella is a foodborne pathogen."
},

{
  question: "The source of bacterial contamination in dental unit waterlines is:",
  answers: [
    "municipal water",
    "backflow from handpieces",
    "backflow from air/water syringes",
    "patients"
  ],
  correct: 0,
  category: "Infection Control",
  rationale: "Municipal water, or safe drinking water, may have up to 500 CFU/mL of bacterial contamination, and therefore this water serves as the source of the bacteria and subsequent biofilm that can grow in dental unit waterlines. The municipal water must be treated or filtered to reduce the number of microorganisms and control the growth of the biofilm. Handpieces and air/water syringes have antiretraction valves that prevent backflow from the patient's mouth into the waterlines."
},

{
  question: "A slime layer that forms in all water environments and allows microorganisms to stick to water containers or tubing is called:",
  answers: [
    "backflow",
    "biofilm",
    "viral load",
    "colonization"
  ],
  correct: 1,
  category: "Infection Control",
  rationale: "Biofilm is formed when water flows through the waterlines and the bacteria in the water adhere to the sides of the lines or tubing. As the bacteria multiply, they form a sticky slime layer that allows the colonies of the bacteria to grow."
},

{
  question: "Preventing or removing biofilm from dental unit waterlines can be accomplished by these methods, except:",
  answers: [
    "in line or point of use filters",
    "self contained water systems and chemical treatments",
    "point of entry filtration systems",
    "flushing waterlines for 20 to 30 seconds"
  ],
  correct: 3,
  category: "Infection Control",
  rationale: "Flushing waterlines removes only the free floating bacteria in the water; it does not remove biofilm from the sides of the waterline tubing. This is accomplished by using waterline cleaner or disinfectants or filtrating the water to remove bacteria and biofilm."
},

{
  question: "Which of the following examples of clinical contact surfaces does not require decontamination after patient treatment?",
  answers: [
    "countertops",
    "light handles",
    "sinks",
    "doorknobs"
  ],
  correct: 2,
  category: "Infection Control",
  rationale: "Sinks are considered housekeeping surfaces and do not require decontamination after each patient."
},

//end at 60 test 1

{
  question: "Which chemical agent is not recommended for use as a surface disinfectant in a dental office?",
  answers: [
    "iodophors",
    "chlorine based products",
    "glutaraldehydes",
    "phenolics"
  ],
  correct: 2,
  category: "Infection Control",
  rationale: "Of the agents listed, glutaraldehydes are not recommended for use as a surface disinfectant in a dental office because they are very toxic and should be handled carefully to avoid the fumes. The other items could be used as a surface disinfectant."
},

{
  question: "An intermediate level surface disinfectant would not kill which microbe?",
  answers: [
    "spores",
    "bacteria",
    "virus",
    "tuberculosis"
  ],
  correct: 0,
  category: "Infection Control",
  rationale: "The intermediate level disinfectant is for killing vegetative bacteria, most fungi, viruses, and Mycobacterium tuberculosis. Spores are killed by sterilization."
},

{
  question: "Which of the following terms indicates the highest level of killing power?",
  answers: [
    "sporicidal agent",
    "bactericidal agent",
    "virucidal agent",
    "tuberculocidal agent"
  ],
  correct: 0,
  category: "Infection Control",
  rationale: "The bacterial endospore is the hardest microorganism to kill. A sterilization method that kills the bacterial endospore is rated as having the highest killing power."
},

{
  question: "Which item listed is not a clinical contact surface?",
  answers: [
    "unit light handle",
    "bracket table switch",
    "sink in the treatment room",
    "air/water syringe"
  ],
  correct: 2,
  category: "Infection Control",
  rationale: "Clinical contact surfaces are those areas that will be touched frequently with gloved hands during routine patient care. The other answers all relate directly to patient care."
},

{
  question: "What should one do to a clinical contact surface after removal of a plastic surface cover and before seating the next patient?",
  answers: [
    "Clean and disinfect with an intermediate level disinfectant and place a new cover.",
    "Clean and disinfect with a low level disinfectant and then add a new cover.",
    "Clean and disinfect with a high level disinfectant and re cover.",
    "If no contamination is present, then place a new plastic cover."
  ],
  correct: 3,
  category: "Infection Control",
  rationale: "After removing a plastic surface cover, the clinical contact surface should be cleaned and disinfected with an intermediate level disinfectant, and then a new cover should be placed."
},

{
  question: "How often should one replace the plastic cover placed over the light handles?",
  answers: [
    "after every patient",
    "at least every half work day",
    "when the cover becomes visibly soiled",
    "only when damage to the cover has occurred"
  ],
  correct: 0,
  category: "Infection Control",
  rationale: "During treatment, these covers have been contaminated and must be changed after each patient. The other answers are not recommended responses."
},

{
  question: "Which Occupational Safety and Health Administration (OSHA) document required for the office contains a plan for postexposure evaluation and follow up?",
  answers: [
    "vaccine declination statement",
    "employee medical record",
    "exposure control plan",
    "written schedule for cleaning and disinfection"
  ],
  correct: 2,
  category: "Infection Control",
  rationale: "The Exposure Control Plan is to contain this information according to the OSHA Bloodborne Pathogens Standard. The vaccine declination statement, employee medical record, and written schedule for cleaning and disinfection are part of this standard, but they do not relate to postexposure evaluation and follow up."
},

{
  question: "After the required OSHA training on bloodborne pathogens is provided at the time of employment, update training is to be given at least every:",
  answers: [
    "4 years",
    "3 years",
    "2 years",
    "1 year"
  ],
  correct: 3,
  category: "Infection Control",
  rationale: "The Occupational Safety and Health Administration (OSHA) Bloodborne Pathogens Standard states that annual training for all employees shall be provided within 1 year of their previous training."
},

{
  question: "Which of the following best describes the Exposure Control Plan required for the office by the Occupational Safety and Health Administration (OSHA)?",
  answers: [
    "what to do in case of a pulp exposure",
    "how to protect against a skin exposure to a hazardous chemical",
    "a healthcare facility's written protocol for reducing contact with bloodborne pathogens",
    "mechanisms to prevent exposure of sensitive teeth to hot and cold temperatures"
  ],
  correct: 2,
  category: "Infection Control",
  rationale: "According to the OSHA Bloodborne Pathogens Standard, the Exposure Control Plan is to contain the exposure determination and a schedule and method of implementation of procedures to comply with the standard."
},

{
  question: "According to OSHA, which document must be in writing and reviewed annually?",
  answers: [
    "Exposure Determination",
    "Post Exposure Protocol",
    "Exposure Control Plan",
    "Hazard Assessment"
  ],
  correct: 2,
  category: "Infection Control",
  rationale: "An Exposure Control Plan, also known as an infection control plan, must be reviewed annually for possible changes, according to the Occupational Safety and Health Administration (OSHA) Bloodborne Pathogens Standard."
},

{
  question: "If a dental assistant punctures a hand with a contaminated instrument while cleaning the instruments, the dental team is required by OSHA to record the injury and:",
  answers: [
    "determine whether a safety device might have prevented the injury",
    "report the injury to a federal or state OSHA office",
    "report the injury to the workers' compensation insurance company",
    "determine how to best clean the contaminated instruments"
  ],
  correct: 0,
  category: "Infection Control",
  rationale: "The Occupational Safety and Health Administration (OSHA) needlestick and sharps injury prevention standard requires dental practices to review injury reports and evaluate whether safety equipment was being used when an injury occurred, whether such equipment could have prevented the injury, and whether changes need to be implemented. In this case, puncture resistant utility gloves may have prevented the injury; the use of an ultrasonic cleaner instead of hand scrubbing may also have prevented the injury."
},

{
  question: "If a dental assistant refuses to be vaccinated for hepatitis B, his or her employer should:",
  answers: [
    "have the assistant's antibody titer tested",
    "dismiss the dental assistant from the practice",
    "provide training for the assistant on hepatitis B transmission",
    "have the assistant sign a declination form"
  ],
  correct: 3,
  category: "Infection Control",
  rationale: "The Occupational Safety and Health Administration (OSHA) Bloodborne Pathogens Standard requires all employers to have at risk employees who refuse the hepatitis B vaccine to sign a declination form, which states that they have been given the opportunity to receive the vaccine but have refused it."
},

{
  question: "A dentist employer is responsible for providing employees with safety information about products, including disinfectants, used in the practice, in the form of:",
  answers: [
    "product labels",
    "Safety Data Sheets",
    "safety posters",
    "personal protective equipment"
  ],
  correct: 1,
  category: "Infection Control",
  rationale: "The Occupational Safety and Health Administration (OSHA) Hazard Communication Standard requires employers to provide Safety Data Sheets to employees, to help make them aware of safety hazards while using the products."
},

{
  question: "A dental assistant must remove a used scalpel blade from a reusable handle. What is the appropriate procedure for removing the blade?",
  answers: [
    "Place the blade end of the handle back inside the foil packet for removal.",
    "Remove the blade with cotton forceps.",
    "Remove the blade with a hemostat.",
    "Place several layers of 2 × 2 gauze over the blade and slide off the handle."
  ],
  correct: 2,
  category: "Infection Control",
  rationale: "The safest way to prevent the scalpel blade from slipping during removal is to secure it with a hemostat, which locks onto the blade."
},

{
  question: "OSHA and the World Health Organization developed a program for standardizing product safety information for chemicals in 2013. This program is called:",
  answers: [
    "Worldwide Safety System (WSS)",
    "Globally Harmonized System (GHS)",
    "Global Safety System (GSS)",
    "Worldwide HazCom System (WHS)"
  ],
  correct: 1,
  category: "Infection Control",
  rationale: "This was an initiative from the United Nations, World Health Organization, and OSHA. It resulted in the 2013 revised OSHA Hazard Communication Standard, which changed Material Safety Data Sheets to Safety Data Sheets and added signal words and pictograms to Safety Data Sheets. It also reformatted hazardous chemical labels that are required on secondary containers."
},

{
  question: "High level disinfectant/sterilant solutions are appropriate for use with items that:",
  answers: [
    "will rust or corrode in a steam sterilizer",
    "are reusable and heat sensitive",
    "are disposable and can be reused",
    "might be dulled by steam sterilization"
  ],
  correct: 1,
  category: "Infection Control",
  rationale: "Only items that can be reused for dental treatment and would be damaged by heat sterilization are appropriate to sterilize in a liquid chemical sterilant."
},

{
  question: "The water quality standard for dental treatment water, as established by the CDC, is:",
  answers: [
    "100 CFU/mL",
    "200 CFU/mL",
    "400 CFU/mL",
    "500 CFU/mL"
  ],
  correct: 3,
  category: "Infection Control",
  rationale: "The Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC) established that the standard for safe drinking water, 500 CFU/mL, is the appropriate one for dental treatment water. Before 2003, the American Dental Association recommended 200 CFU/mL, but the CDC guideline is the prevailing standard."
},

{
  question: "If a community is under a “boil water” alert, what type of water should be used for patient rinsing and handwashing?",
  answers: [
    "dental unit water",
    "tap water",
    "bottled or distilled water",
    "sterile water"
  ],
  correct: 2,
  category: "Infection Control",
  rationale: "In the event of a boil water alert in a community, bottled or distilled water should be used for handwashing and patient rinsing to prevent exposure to dangerous levels of microbial contamination."
},

{
  question: "To decontaminate a dental impression, the dental assistant should:",
  answers: [
    "immerse the impression or spray it with disinfectant",
    "rinse with warm water, shake out excess, and allow to air dry",
    "immerse the impression or spray with a high level disinfectant",
    "rinse with warm water, and spray or immerse in a disinfectant"
  ],
  correct: 3,
  category: "Infection Control",
  rationale: "Impressions should be rinsed to remove blood and saliva and then either sprayed with an intermediate level disinfectant or immersed in the disinfectant for the appropriate contact time."
},

{
  question: "When a soap container is empty or partially empty, how should it be refilled?",
  answers: [
    "It can be topped off whenever the soap level is below half full.",
    "The outside of the container can be disinfected and then refilled.",
    "The container should be empty, disinfected inside and out, and then refilled.",
    "The container should be discarded and a new container used each time."
  ],
  correct: 3,
  category: "Infection Control",
  rationale: "Soap containers may become contaminated from touching with dirty hands; therefore the container should be cleaned and disinfected when empty and then refilled—never topped off. The use of touch free soap dispensers helps to reduce the potential for contamination of the containers and soap."
},

{
  question: "If a dental assistant experiences skin irritation after wearing latex examination gloves, he or she should:",
  answers: [
    "discontinue the use of latex gloves and wear nonlatex gloves",
    "wear nonlatex gloves and seek medical advice regarding latex hypersensitivity",
    "wear a cotton glove liner underneath the latex gloves",
    "assume that he or she is latex allergic and avoid all products containing latex"
  ],
  correct: 1,
  category: "Infection Control",
  rationale: "Any time a dental assistant experiences dermatitis from wearing gloves, the use of latex gloves (if worn) should be discontinued, and the dental assistant should seek medical attention to determine the cause of the dermatitis. Nonintact skin can serve as a portal for infection and should be treated as a potentially serious health hazard. In addition, if the dermatitis is from a true latex hypersensitivity or allergy, it can be life threatening, and a specific diagnosis should be sought so that appropriate precautions can be taken."
},

{
  question: "If a patient indicates latex hypersensitivity on the medical history, the dental practice must:",
  answers: [
    "make sure that the medical emergency kit is up to date",
    "wear nonlatex gloves for all that patient's dental treatment",
    "provide latex free items for all of that patient's treatment",
    "note the latex allergy in the patient's clinical chart and check for signs of allergy"
  ],
  correct: 2,
  category: "Infection Control",
  rationale: "Although the practice should certainly note the information in the patient's record and wear nonlatex gloves, there are other items, such as prophy cups, that may contain latex. The practice must provide a latex safe environment for the patient, which involves evaluating all items and materials for latex content."
},

{
  question: "Which of the following incidents is not considered an exposure incident?",
  answers: [
    "splash of blood onto chapped or abraded skin",
    "puncture with a contaminated needle or instrument",
    "spatter of blood or saliva into eyes",
    "puncture with a needle before injection"
  ],
  correct: 3,
  category: "Infection Control",
  rationale: "Although a needlestick with an unused needle is an injury to a dental healthcare worker, it poses no risk of exposure, because it is not contaminated."
},

{
  question: "Which activity is contraindicated during the use of nitrous oxide in conscious sedation?",
  answers: [
    "Maintain a conversation with the patient.",
    "Use a dental dam when applicable.",
    "Use a scavenger system.",
    "Secure the patient's mask."
  ],
  correct: 3,
  category: "Infection Control",
  rationale: "During the use of nitrous oxide, you should avoid having a conversation with the patient because this will cause movement of the nasal mask and create potential gas leaks around the mask."
},

{
  question: "The Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC) recommends that dental office sterilizers be biologically monitored how frequently?",
  answers: [
    "weekly",
    "biweekly",
    "monthly",
    "bimonthly"
  ],
  correct: 0,
  category: "Infection Control",
  rationale: "The CDC recommends that sterilizers be biologically monitored weekly."
},

{
  question: "In 2013 the new OSHA Hazard Communication Standard introduced new hazard symbols to be included on Safety Data Sheets and product labels. These include diagrams that represent certain health or physical hazards and are called:",
  answers: [
    "icons",
    "warnings",
    "images",
    "pictograms"
  ],
  correct: 3,
  category: "Infection Control",
  rationale: "The 2013 revised OSHA Hazard Communication Standard incorporates the Globally Harmonized System (GHS) of chemical hazard warnings, which includes signal words and pictograms that are displayed on product labels and on Safety Data Sheets."
},

{
  question: "Which of the following types of tissue(s) can be damaged by failure to use proper ergonomic techniques?",
  answers: [
    "muscles",
    "joints",
    "tendons",
    "all of the above"
  ],
  correct: 3,
  category: "Infection Control",
  rationale: "Improper ergonomics can cause pain and damage to muscles, joints, tendons, and ligaments."
},

{
  question: "What is the term for the type of waste material that cannot be disposed in the regular trash?",
  answers: [
    "contaminated waste",
    "medical waste",
    "toxic waste",
    "regulated waste"
  ],
  correct: 3,
  category: "Infection Control",
  rationale: "Toxic waste is poisonous and contains substances such as arsenic, barium, mercury, lead, and so forth. Contaminated waste includes nonregulated waste such as patient bibs and saliva soaked gauze. Regulated waste includes sharps, blood soaked or blood caked items, human tissue, and pathology samples. Medical waste includes any solid waste that is generated in the diagnosis or treatment. Only a small percentage of medical waste is infectious and has to be regulated."
},

{
  question: "How should instruments with hinges (e.g., scissors, forceps, pliers) be positioned in the sterilizer?",
  answers: [
    "Hinged instruments should be positioned with the hinges open.",
    "Hinged instruments should be positioned with the hinges closed.",
    "Either of the above is acceptable because the steam or chemical vapor will penetrate the hinged areas.",
    "Wipe hinged area of instrument with a high level disinfectant before placing in sterilizer."
  ],
  correct: 0,
  category: "Infection Control",
  rationale: "Open hinges allow the steam or chemical vapor to come in contact with all surfaces. Closed hinges prevent the chemical vapor from coming in contact with all surfaces."
},

{
  question: "Which of the following errors will not result in a failure of sterilization?",
  answers: [
    "improper loading",
    "inadequate time",
    "faulty seals on the chamber door",
    "failure to use a process indicator"
  ],
  correct: 3,
  category: "Infection Control",
  rationale: "A process indicator is used to verify that the item has been exposed to sterilizing conditions (i.e., heat or chemical vapors), but it is not one of the factors necessary for sterilization to occur. Improper loading, inadequate time, and faulty seals on the chamber door are the factors that will cause a sterilization failure."
},

{
  question: "Which of the following are methods by which dental personnel can be exposed to infectious diseases?",
  answers: [
    "direct contact with blood and saliva",
    "indirect contact with contaminated instruments",
    "aerosol, splatter, and splashes in the eyes or mouth",
    "all of the above may cause redness and irritation"
  ],
  correct: 2,
  category: "Infection Control",
  rationale: "Dental personnel can be exposed to infectious diseases by all of the methods."
},

{
  question: "Redness and irritation of the hands of dental professionals can be caused by:",
  answers: [
    "allergy to latex gloves",
    "not thoroughly drying hands after washing",
    "sensitivity to chemicals used in the production of the gloves",
    "all of the conditions above"
  ],
  correct: 3,
  category: "Infection Control",
  rationale: "Redness and irritation to the hands can be caused by all of the conditions listed."
},

{
  question: "An instrument that touches the mucous membranes but will not penetrate soft tissue or touch bone is classified as:",
  answers: [
    "critical",
    "semicritical",
    "noncritical",
    "both critical and semicritical"
  ],
  correct: 1,
  category: "Infection Control",
  rationale: "Critical instruments are designed to penetrate soft tissues, and noncritical instruments do not touch the mucous membranes. Semicritical instruments are those that do touch mucous membranes but are not used to penetrate soft tissue or touch bone."
},

{
  question: "Which of the following disinfectants tend to cause a reddish or yellow stain?",
  answers: [
    "alcohol",
    "phenol",
    "bleach",
    "iodophors"
  ],
  correct: 3,
  category: "Infection Control",
  rationale: "Iodophor disinfectants contain iodine and therefore can leave a reddish or yellow stain."
},

{
  question: "What is the preferred method of cleaning contaminated instruments before sterilization?",
  answers: [
    "placing the instruments in the ultrasonic cleaner",
    "hand scrubbing the instruments with a stiff brush",
    "holding instruments under a hard spray of water",
    "instruments in a blood solvent"
  ],
  correct: 0,
  category: "Infection Control",
  rationale: "Placing the instruments in the ultrasonic cleaner is the only safe method because there is no handling of the instruments."
},

{
  question: "What is the major disadvantage of using a chemical vapor sterilizer?",
  answers: [
    "Rusting can occur.",
    "Adequate ventilation and/or purging is necessary.",
    "Instruments are wet at the end of cycle.",
    "The process is longer than for an autoclave."
  ],
  correct: 1,
  category: "Infection Control",
  rationale: "Inhalation of chemical vapors is a health hazard that is more serious than rusting instruments, wet instruments, or a longer processing time."
},

{
  question: "All dental professionals must use surgical masks and protective eyewear to protect the eyes and face:",
  answers: [
    "only during surgical procedures when handpieces are utilized",
    "whenever a patient has respiratory symptoms",
    "whenever spatter and aerosolized blood and saliva are likely",
    "whenever respiratory protection is available"
  ],
  correct: 2,
  category: "Infection Control",
  rationale: "In accordance with OSHA recommendations, surgical masks and protective eyewear are to be worn whenever splashes, spray, spatter, or droplets of blood or saliva may be generated and eye, nose, or mouth contamination may occur."
},

{
  question: "All dental assistants must undergo routine training in:",
  answers: [
    "infection control, safety protocols, and hazard communication",
    "charting, taking patients' vital signs, and using the office intercom system",
    "infection control, uniform sizing, and ordering of disposables",
    "hazardous waste, management, charting, and application of dental dams"
  ],
  correct: 0,
  category: "Infection Control",
  rationale: "Infection control, safety protocols, and hazard communication are all requirements of OSHA and are requirements for all employees in a dental practice. Many of the other activities mentioned in b, c, and d are common to duties for the assistants they are not required by OSHA."
},

{
  question: "According to OSHA, employers must require all employees to be vaccinated for:",
  answers: [
    "hepatitis B, influenza, and MMWR",
    "vaccinations cannot be required",
    "influenza, Tdap, and MMWR",
    "hepatitis B, hepatitis C, and influenza"
  ],
  correct: 1,
  category: "Infection Control",
  rationale: "Vaccinations cannot be required by employers. OSHA states that employers must provide the vaccine at no cost to the employees. Influenza, Tdap, and MMR vaccines are recommended by the CDC, and there is no vaccine for hepatitis C."
},

{
  question: "If a high level disinfectant is tested for concentration, and the solution is not at the optimal level for use, it should be:",
  answers: [
    "changed when the maximum use time has been reached",
    "changed at the end of the day that it is tested",
    "changed immediately if the concentration is not optimal",
    "changed weekly so that testing the concentration is not needed"
  ],
  correct: 2,
  category: "Infection Control",
  rationale: "Changed immediately if the concentration is not optimal, because the solution is tested for efficacy at a specific concentration. As items are added into the solution that are wet, the solution becomes diluted over time."
},

{
  "question": "Which pathogen can be transmitted through the inhalation of airborne droplet nuclei?",
  "answers": [
    "hepatitis B",
    "Candida albicans",
    "M. tuberculosis",
    "human immunodeficiency virus"
  ],
  "correct": "2",
  "category": "Infection Control",
  "rationale": "Mycobacterium tuberculosis is carried in airborne particles, called droplet nuclei. Hepatitis B is a bloodborne pathogen spread through the exchange of body fluids, mainly blood, semen, and vaginal secretions. Candida albicans is a species of yeastlike fungi that are part of normal human flora and spread by contact with excretions of mouth, skin, and feces. The human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) is a bloodborne pathogen spread through the exchange of body fluids, mainly blood, semen, and vaginal secretions."
},

{
  "question": "What is transmitted by consuming contaminated food or water?",
  "answers": [
    "hepatitis A virus (HAV)",
    "hepatitis B virus (HBV)",
    "hepatitis C virus (HCV)",
    "human immunodeficiency virus (HIV)"
  ],
  "correct": "0",
  "category": "Infection Control",
  "rationale": "Hepatitis A virus (HAV) is transmitted by the fecal oral route, either through person to person contact or consumption of contaminated food or water. Hepatitis B virus (HBV), hepatitis C virus (HCV), and human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) are bloodborne pathogens. A bloodborne pathogen or disease is one that can be spread by contact and contamination by blood."
},

{
  "question": "Which term describes the strength or capacity of a pathogen to cause disease?",
  "answers": [
    "sepsis",
    "virulence",
    "bioburden",
    "disinfectant"
  ],
  "correct": "1",
  "category": "Infection Control",
  "rationale": "Virulence is defined as the strength or ability of a pathogen to produce disease. Sepsis is a pathologic state characterized by the presence of pathogens. Bioburden is any organic material that interferes with the sterilization process. A disinfectant is a chemical used to destroy some forms of pathogenic microorganisms."
},

{
  "question": "Which type of transmission can occur via contaminated dental instruments, equipment, or records?",
  "answers": [
    "direct",
    "indirect",
    "inhalation",
    "person to person"
  ],
  "correct": "1",
  "category": "Infection Control",
  "rationale": "Indirect transmission occurs via contaminated dental instruments, equipment, or records. Direct transmission occurs when there is physical contact between an infected person and a susceptible person. Inhalation transmission is person to person transmission of pathogens through the air by means of inhalation of infectious particles. Person to person transmission is synonymous with direct transmission."
},

{
  "question": "If a disease is transmitted through an inanimate object, what is the object termed?",
  "answers": [
    "carrier",
    "vector",
    "vehicle",
    "transferor"
  ],
  "correct": "2",
  "category": "Infection Control",
  "rationale": "A vehicle is an inanimate object that can transmit disease. A carrier is a person or organism that is infected with an infectious disease agent but displays no symptoms. A vector is a live organism that can transmit disease. A transferor is not a term used in disease transmission but is defined as one who conveys a title, right, or property."
},

{
  "question": "What is the mode of transmission for Mycobacterium tuberculosis?",
  "answers": [
    "fomites",
    "tainted water",
    "airborne particles",
    "contaminated food"
  ],
  "correct": "2",
  "category": "Infection Control",
  "rationale": "Mycobacterium tuberculosis is carried in airborne particles. A vector is an organism that transmits a disease or parasite from one animal or plant to another and does not transmit M. tuberculosis. Tainted water and contaminated food are not transmission routes for M. tuberculosis."
},

{
  "question": "An employee who refuses which vaccination must sign a declination form that the employer retains?",
  "answers": [
    "HBV",
    "MMR",
    "tetanus",
    "influenza"
  ],
  "correct": "0",
  "category": "Infection Control",
  "rationale": "An employee who declines the hepatitis B virus (HBV) vaccine must sign a declination form that the employer keeps on file. Refusal of the measles, mumps, and rubella (MMR), tetanus, or influenza vaccine does not require signing a declination form."
},

{
  "question": "What offers the best protection against hepatitis B virus (HBV) infection?",
  "answers": [
    "vaccination",
    "hand disinfection",
    "protective eyewear",
    "fluid resistant mask"
  ],
  "correct": "0",
  "category": "Infection Control",
  "rationale": "The HBV vaccination is the best protection against hepatitis B virus (HBV) infection. Hand sanitation is a component of practicing standard precautions but is not the best protection against hepatitis B virus (HBV) infection. Wearing protective eyewear and a fluid resistant mask are examples of personal protective equipment (PPE) and necessary when practicing infection control."
},

{
  "question": "What kind of immunity is established as a result of vaccination?",
  "answers": [
    "innate",
    "natural",
    "passive",
    "artificial"
  ],
  "correct": "3",
  "category": "Infection Control",
  "rationale": "Artificially acquired immunity is induced by a vaccine that contains the antigen. Innate immunity and natural immunity are synonymous terms that denote a natural resistance with which a person is born. Passive immunity is the transfer of active immunity, in the form of ready made antibodies, from one individual to another."
},

{
  "question": "Which diagnostic test is utilized to identify active tuberculosis?",
  "answers": [
    "chest x ray",
    "Mantoux test",
    "tuberculin skin test (TST)",
    "purified protein derivative (PPD)"
  ],
  "correct": "0",
  "category": "Infection Control",
  "rationale": "Active tuberculosis is determined through a chest x ray examination or sputum sample culture. The Mantoux test, tuberculin skin test (TST), and purified protein derivative (PPD) are all names synonymous with a skin test that involves injecting a solution under the skin on the underside of the forearm. This skin test determines exposure to Mycobacterium tuberculosis but not active tuberculosis."
},

{
  "question": "What is the first item of personal protective equipment (PPE) to be removed after completing a dental treatment procedure?",
  "answers": [
    "mask",
    "gloves",
    "lab jacket",
    "safety glasses"
  ],
  "correct": "1",
  "category": "Infection Control",
  "rationale": "Gloves are the first item of PPE removed after completion of a dental treatment procedure. "
},

{
  "question": "What is the recommended length for natural nail tips?",
  "answers": [
    "1/4 inch",
    "1/2 inch",
    "3/4 inch",
    "1 inch"
  ],
  "correct": "0",
  "category": "Infection Control",
  "rationale": "According to the CDC Hand Hygiene Guideline, natural nail tips should be kept at ¼ inch or less. Answers b, c, and d are incorrect answers."
},

{
  "question": "What should be done after removing an alginate impression from a patient's mouth?",
  "answers": [
    "Soak the impression in water and disinfect.",
    "Leave the impression out to air dry.",
    "Rinse with water then disinfect.",
    "Disinfect by immersing in a high level disinfectant."
  ],
  "correct": "2",
  "category": "Infection Control",
  "rationale": "Impressions are rinsed and disinfected immediately after removal from the patient's mouth. Soaking the impression in water would cause imbibition. Leaving the impression out to air dry would distort the impression. Sterilizing the impression in a chemical vapor sterilizer would distort the impression."
},

{
  "question": "Which of the following is a single use disposable item?",
  "answers": [
    "metal prophy angle",
    "level 3 face mask",
    "dental explorer",
    "XCP film holder"
  ],
  "correct": "1",
  "category": "Infection Control",
  "rationale": "A face mask is a single use disposable item because it cannot be rinsed and disinfected or sterilized. Metal prophy angles, dental explorer, or XCP film holder can be sterilized in an autoclave."
},

{
  "question": "Which item is considered regulated waste in the field of dentistry?",
  "answers": [
    "gloves",
    "empty anesthetic carpule",
    "patient bib",
    "blood saturated gauze"
  ],
  "correct": "3",
  "category": "Infection Control",
  "rationale": "Any blood saturated item should be placed in the hazardous waste container. Gloves can be placed in the regular trash. An empty anesthetic carpule can be disposed of in the regular trash. A patient bib can be disposed of in the regular trash."
},

{
  "question": "Which scenario is an example of direct disease transmission?",
  "answers": [
    "coughing and sneezing",
    "contact with a contaminated counter",
    "contact with oral fluids",
    "contact with contaminated dental instruments"
  ],
  "correct": "2",
  "category": "Infection Control",
  "rationale": " Contact with oral fluids is an example of direct disease transmission. Coughing, contact with a contaminated counter, and contact with contaminated dental instruments are examples of indirect disease transmission."
},

{
  "question": "Which disease is spread by droplet transmission?",
  "answers": [
    "tuberculosis",
    "hepatitis B (HBV)",
    "hepatitis C (HCV)",
    "human immunodeficiency virus (HIV)"
  ],
  "correct": "0",
  "category": "Infection Control",
  "rationale": "Tuberculosis is spread through droplet transmission. Hepatitis B virus (HBV), hepatitis C virus (HCV), and human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) are bloodborne pathogens contracted through direct transmission."
},

{
  "question": "What type of disease transmission could occur if a dental assistant suffers a needlestick injury?",
  "answers": [
    "vector",
    "droplet",
    "airborne",
    "parenteral"
  ],
  "correct": "3",
  "category": "Infection Control",
  "rationale": "Parenteral transmission occurs through breaks in the skin, such as a needlestick. Vector transmission occurs when any agent transmits an infectious pathogen into another living organism such as via an insect bite. Droplet transmission occurs when bacteria or viruses travel on relatively large respiratory droplets that people sneeze, cough, drip, or exhale. Airborne transmission occurs when bacteria or viruses travel on dust particles or on small respiratory droplets that may become aerosolized."
},

{
  "question": "Which tool could lead to droplet transmission of disease?",
  "answers": [
    "syringe needle",
    "contaminated counter",
    "high-speed handpiece",
    "high-volume evacuator"
  ],
  "correct": "2",
  "category": "Infection Control",
  "rationale": "A high-speed handpiece produces an aerosol that can transmit disease through droplets. A syringe needle can produce an indirect parenteral transmission. A contaminated dental counter and high-volume evacuator would be indirect modes of disease transmission."
},

{
  "question": "When is it necessary to perform hand hygiene?",
  "answers": [
    "before placement of gloves only",
    "after removal of gloves only",
    "before placement of gloves and after removal of gloves",
    "hand hygiene is performed only when hands are soiled before placement or after removal"
  ],
  "correct": "2",
  "category": "Infection Control",
  "rationale": "The Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC) recommendation for hand antisepsis in relationship to gloves is that hand hygiene should be performed before the placement of gloves and after the removal of gloves. Washing hands only before placement of gloves is not correct because hands may have become contaminated during the wearing of gloves as a result of microscopic openings in the gloves. Performing hand hygiene only after the removal of gloves is not correct because bacteria on the hands may be transmitted to the patient through microscopic openings in the gloves. No hand hygiene before placement or after removal of gloves leaves both the operator and the patient at risk of exposure to infection."
},

{
  "question": "Which gloves are utilized for disinfecting the operatory and processing instruments?",
  "answers": [
    "over gloves",
    "utility gloves",
    "examination gloves",
    "prepackaged sterilized gloves"
  ],
  "correct": "1",
  "category": "Infection Control",
  "rationale": "Utility gloves are used when disinfecting the operatory and processing instruments. Over gloves are worn over examination (treatment) gloves. Over gloves are not designed to replace examination gloves. Examination gloves, also known as treatment gloves, are designed for a single use. They are nonsterile and ambidextrous. Prepackaged sterilized gloves are intended for one-time use in surgical procedures."
},

{
  "question": "Which type of gloves are not designed for single use?",
  "answers": [
    "over gloves",
    "utility gloves",
    "examination gloves",
    "prepackaged sterilized gloves"
  ],
  "correct": "1",
  "category": "Infection Control",
  "rationale": "Utility gloves are cleaned and disinfected after use and are used more than one time. Over gloves are worn over examination gloves and are disposed of after use. Examination gloves are used during patient treatment and are designed for a single use. Prepackaged sterilized gloves are intended for one-time use in surgical procedures."
},

{
  "question": "Which of the following is not a bloodborne virus?",
  "answers": [
    "hepatitis B virus",
    "hepatitis C virus",
    "varicella-zoster virus",
    "human immunodeficiency virus (HIV)"
  ],
  "correct": "2",
  "category": "Infection Control",
  "rationale": "Varicella-zoster virus is the source of chickenpox and is not a bloodborne pathogen. The virus spreads in the air when an infected person coughs or sneezes. It can also be spread by touching or breathing in the virus particles. Hepatitis B virus, hepatitis C virus, and human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) are bloodborne pathogens."
},

{
  "question": "Which mode of disease transmission could occur if a dental assistant does not disinfect a countertop in a contaminated treatment room?",
  "answers": [
    "direct",
    "indirect",
    "droplet",
    "airborne"
  ],
  "correct": "1",
  "category": "Infection Control",
  "rationale": "Indirect transmission occurs when an inanimate object or material, called a fomite, becomes contaminated with an infectious agent. Direct disease transmission occurs when infectious diseases are spread directly through personal contact, such as touching, biting, kissing, or sexual intercourse."
},

{
  "question": "Which mode of disease transmission could occur if a dental assistant does not wear examination gloves when taking an alginate impression?",
  "answers": [
    "direct",
    "indirect",
    "droplet",
    "airborne"
  ],
  "correct": "0",
  "category": "Infection Control",
  "rationale": "Direct disease transmission occurs when infectious diseases are spread directly through personal contact, such as touching, biting, kissing, or sexual intercourse."
},

{
  "question": "Which mode of disease transmission could occur if a dental assistant doesn't wear a mask when assisting a dentist using a high-speed handpiece?",
  "answers": [
    "direct",
    "indirect",
    "parenteral",
    "airborne"
  ],
  "correct": "3",
  "category": "Infection Control",
  "rationale": "A high-speed handpiece produces an aerosol that can transmit disease through airborne droplets. Direct disease transmission occurs when infectious diseases are spread directly through personal contact, such as touching, biting, kissing, or sexual intercourse. Vector-borne transmission is an indirect transmission of an infectious agent that occurs when a vector bites or touches a person. Vehicle transmission occurs when an inanimate object or material, called a fomite, becomes contaminated with an infectious agent."
},

{
  "question": "Which mode of disease transmission can happen if a dental assistant fails to properly sterilize contaminated dental instruments?",
  "answers": [
    "direct",
    "indirect",
    "droplet",
    "airborne"
  ],
  "correct": "1",
  "category": "Infection Control",
  "rationale": "Indirect transmission occurs when an inanimate object or material, called a fomite, becomes contaminated with an infectious agent. Direct disease transmission occurs when infectious diseases are spread directly through personal contact, such as touching, biting, kissing, or sexual intercourse."
},

{
  "question": "Which of the following is an example of personal protective equipment (PPE)?",
  "answers": [
    "gloves",
    "autoclave",
    "surface barriers",
    "hand hygiene"
  ],
  "correct": "0",
  "category": "Infection Control",
  "rationale": "Gloves are classified as personal protective equipment (PPE). PPE refers to protective clothing, goggles, or other garments designed to protect the wearer's body from infection. An autoclave is an apparatus using superheated steam under pressure for sterilizing. Surface barriers are an additional protection used to lessen the need for surface disinfectant or to shield surfaces that are difficult to disinfect in a treatment room. Hand disinfection reduces or inhibits the growth of microorganisms by the application of an antiseptic hand rub or by performing an antiseptic hand wash."
},

{
  "question": "Which of the following is a single-use disposable item?",
  "answers": [
    "explorer",
    "cotton pliers",
    "position indicator device",
    "saliva ejector"
  ],
  "correct": "3",
  "category": "Infection Control",
  "rationale": "A saliva ejector is manufactured and identified as a single-use item because it cannot be sterilized or disinfected after use. Dental explorers, cotton pliers, and PIDs can be sterilized for reuse."
},

{
  "question": "On which item would a surface barrier not be placed to reduce the need for surface disinfectant?",
  "answers": [
    "dental chair",
    "light handles",
    "radiographic head",
    "instrument cassette"
  ],
  "correct": "3",
  "category": "Infection Control",
  "rationale": "An instrument cassette can be sterilized and does not require a surface barrier. Dental chairs, light handles, and radiographic heads would benefit from the placement of a surface barrier."
},

{
  "question": "Which term is defined as an inanimate object that can harbor pathogens?",
  "answers": [
    "fomite",
    "vector",
    "droplet",
    "vapor"
  ],
  "correct": 0,
  "category": "Infection Control",
  "rationale": "A fomite refers to any inanimate object, such as a towel or a doorknob, that when contaminated with infectious agents, can transfer disease."
},

{
  "question": "Which could transmit disease via droplet?",
  "answers": [
    "sneezing",
    "countertop",
    "patient chart",
    "thermometer"
  ],
  "correct": 0,
  "category": "Infection Control",
  "rationale": "Droplet transmission involves the spread of pathogens through small droplets that are expelled when a person coughs, sneezes, or talks."
},

{
  "question": "Which term is defined as the strength of a pathogen to cause disease?",
  "answers": [
    "sepsis",
    "infection",
    "virulence",
    "bioburden"
  ],
  "correct": 2,
  "category": "Infection Control",
  "rationale": "Virulence refers to the ability of a pathogen or microorganism to cause disease."
},

{
  "question": "Which type of disease transmission occurs if a paper dental chart is handled by a dental assistant while wearing contaminated gloves, then handed to the business assistant?",
  "answers": [
    "direct",
    "droplet",
    "indirect",
    "airborne"
  ],
  "correct": 2,
  "category": "Infection Control",
  "rationale": "This is an example of indirect transmission, as the pathogen is transferred from one person to another through an intermediate object, in this case, the dental chart."
},

{
  "question": "Which term is defined as items that penetrate soft tissue and come in direct contact with bone, blood, and other body fluids?",
  "answers": [
    "critical items",
    "noncritical items",
    "semicritical items",
    "disposable items"
  ],
  "correct": 0,
  "category": "Infection Control",
  "rationale": "Critical items in healthcare are those that come into contact with sterile tissue or the vascular system and should be sterilized before each use."
},

{
  "question": "Which is an example of a noncritical item in instrument processing and sterilization?",
  "answers": [
    "scaler",
    "scalpel blades",
    "dental handpiece",
    "shade guide"
  ],
  "correct": 3,
  "category": "Infection Control",
  "rationale": "A shade guide, which does not directly contact mucous membranes, is considered a noncritical item. It should be thoroughly cleaned and receive low-level disinfection between patients."
},

{
  "question": "Which is an example of a semicritical item in instrument processing and sterilization?",
  "answers": [
    "stethoscope",
    "pulse oximeter",
    "surgical dental bur",
    "dental mouth mirror"
  ],
  "correct": 3,
  "category": "Infection Control",
  "rationale": "A dental mouth mirror, which contacts mucous membranes but does not penetrate soft tissue, is considered a semicritical item. It should be cleaned and sterilized or receive high-level disinfection between patients."
},

{
  "question": "Which is classified as regulated waste in the dental office?",
  "answers": [
    "endodontic file",
    "surface barrier",
    "saliva-soaked gauze",
    "contaminated patient bib"
  ],
  "correct": 0,
  "category": "Infection Control",
  "rationale": "An endodontic file is classified as regulated waste. The OSHA Bloodborne Pathogens Standard classifies regulated and nonregulated waste in the dental office. Surface barriers, saliva-stained gauze, and a contaminated patient bib are classified as nonregulated waste according to the OSHA Bloodborne Pathogens Standard."
},

{
  "question": "Which is classified as nonregulated waste in the dental office?",
  "answers": [
    "needles",
    "surface barrier",
    "blood-stained gauze",
    "contaminated broken glass"
  ],
  "correct": 1,
  "category": "Infection Control",
  "rationale": "Nonregulated waste is waste that poses no risk of causing infection during handling and disposal. This includes items like surface barriers, which have not been in contact with blood or other potentially infectious materials."
},

{
  "question": "The most accurate way to ensure that proper sterilization of instruments has occurred is to __________.",
  "answers": [
    "use biologic indicators",
    "monitor the length of time in the autoclave",
    "check the pressure gauges on the autoclave",
    "feel if the instruments are warm after sterilization"
  ],
  "correct": 0,
  "category": "Infection Control",
  "rationale": "Biologic indicators are the most definitive means of confirming that sterilization has occurred, because they assess the sterilization process directly by killing known, highly resistant organisms (usually Geobacillus stearothermophilus)."
},

// 41 - 50
  {
    "question": "Which type of sterilization used in the dental office requires the highest temperature?",
    "answers": ["dry heat", "unsaturated chemical vapor", "flash or immediate use sterilizer", "steam autoclave"],
    "correct": 0,
    "category": "Infection Control",
    "rationale": "#"
  },
  {
    "question": "How should a dental assistant determine the amount of time required for sterilization to occur when using a chemical liquid sterilization process for heat-sensitive instruments?",
    "answers": ["10 hours", "6 hours", "it depends on the concentration", "follow the manufacturer’s instructions"],
    "correct": 3,
    "category": "Infection Control",
    "rationale": "#"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which can occur if wet dental instrument packages are removed from the autoclave before the drying cycle is completed?",
    "answers": ["wicking", "aerating", "saturating", "ventilating"],
    "correct": 0,
    "category": "Infection Control",
    "rationale": "#"
  },
  {
    "question": "The solution in the ultrasonic cleaner should be replaced at least __________",
    "answers": ["once a day", "once a week", "once a month", "every other day"],
    "correct": 0,
    "category": "Infection Control",
    "rationale": "#"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which type of gloves are worn during instrument processing?",
    "answers": ["over gloves", "utility gloves", "examination gloves", "sterile gloves"],
    "correct": 1,
    "category": "Infection Control",
    "rationale": "#"
  },
  {
    "question": "A small sheet of __________ can be submerged in the ultrasonic unit to determine whether the ultrasonic cleaner is working properly.",
    "answers": ["copper", "plastic", "wax paper", "aluminum foil"],
    "correct": 3,
    "category": "Sterilization",
    "rationale": "#"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which is the process that is initiated in the ultrasonic cleaner when sound waves are produced?",
    "answers": ["cavitation", "sterilization", "disinfection", "sanitization"],
    "correct": 0,
    "category": "Infection Control",
    "rationale": "#"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which term refers to the blood, saliva, and tissue fluids that contaminate dental instruments after use?",
    "answers": ["organic", "syneresis", "bioburden", "bacteremia"],
    "correct": 2,
    "category": "Infection Control",
    "rationale": "#"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which sterilization technique may rust non–stainless steel instruments and burs?",
    "answers": ["steam autoclave", "dry heat oven type", "rapid heat transfer", "unsaturated chemical vapor"],
    "correct": 0,
    "category": "Infection Control",
    "rationale": "#"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which type of sterilization monitoring technique is a multiparameter indicator of the sterilization process?",
    "answers": ["process indicator", "biologic monitor", "chemical integrator", "physical monitoring"],
    "correct": 2,
    "category": "Infection Control",
    "rationale": "#"
  },

  //51 - 60

  {
    "question": "Which is the purpose of placing contaminated dental instruments in a presoaking solution?",
    "answers": ["removes bioburden", "disinfects the instruments", "kills the highest level of spores", "prevents debris from drying on the instruments"],
    "correct": 3,
    "category": "Infection Control",
    "rationale": "#"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which is not an item of personal protective equipment (PPE) that is worn during the manual scrubbing of contaminated dental instruments?",
    "answers": ["face mask", "dosimeter", "utility gloves", "protective eyewear"],
    "correct": 1,
    "category": "Infection Control",
    "rationale": "#"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which method of sterilization is used to sterilize unpackaged instruments using a short exposure time?",
    "answers": ["dry heat oven", "steam autoclave", "flash sterilization", "unsaturated chemical vapor"],
    "correct": 2,
    "category": "Infection Control",
    "rationale": "#"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which is an improper technique regarding infection control in the dental office?",
    "answers": ["eating in the dental laboratory", "storing sterile instruments in sealed bags", "disposing of a patient bib in the general trash", "using over gloves to open a drawer in the treatment room"],
    "correct": 0,
    "category": "Infection Control",
    "rationale": "#"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which is classified as a high-level disinfectant?",
    "answers": ["phenolics", "iodophors", "glutaraldehyde", "sodium hypochlorite"],
    "correct": 2,
    "category": "Infection Control",
    "rationale": "#"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which is classified as a low-level disinfectant?",
    "answers": ["phenolics", "hydrogen peroxide", "glutaraldehyde", "quaternary amine"],
    "correct": 3,
    "category": "Infection Control",
    "rationale": "#"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which is the recommended time frame for an operator to change a facial mask under standard precautions?",
    "answers": ["every hour", "once a day", "twice a day", "after each patient"],
    "correct": 3,
    "category": "Infection Control",
    "rationale": "#"
  },
  {
    "question": "When should an alcohol hand rub be used for routine dentistry?",
    "answers": ["at the beginning of the day", "immediately after handwashing", "in the absence of visible soil", "immediately before handwashing"],
    "correct": 2,
    "category": "Infection Control",
    "rationale": "#"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which disinfectant is an iodine-containing compound?",
    "answers": ["phenolics", "iodophors", "glutaraldehyde", "quaternary amine"],
    "correct": 1,
    "category": "Infection Control",
    "rationale": "#"
  },
  {
    "question": "How often should sodium hypochlorite disinfectant be prepared?",
    "answers": ["daily", "weekly", "monthly", "bimonthly"],
    "correct": 0,
    "category": "Infection Control",
    "rationale": "#"
  },

 // 61 - 70

  {
    "question": "Indicators of which type are printed on packing materials for sterilization and contain dyes that change color on exposure to sterilizing cycles?",
    "answers": ["process indicator", "biologic monitor", "process integrator", "physical monitoring"],
    "correct": 0,
    "category": "Infection Control",
    "rationale": "#"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which chemical is not recommended as a disinfectant?",
    "answers": ["alcohol", "iodophors", "glutaraldehyde", "quaternary amine"],
    "correct": 0,
    "category": "Infection Control",
    "rationale": "#"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which bacterium is hard to kill in the sterilization process because of its lipid cell wall?",
    "answers": ["Streptococcus", "Pseudomonas", "Staphylococcus", "M. tuberculosis"],
    "correct": 3,
    "category": "Infection Control",
    "rationale": "#"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which disinfectant produces fumes that are toxic to lung tissue?",
    "answers": ["phenolics", "iodophors", "glutaraldehyde", "quaternary amine"],
    "correct": 2,
    "category": "Infection Control",
    "rationale": "#"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which is the process that kills microorganisms, including bacterial spores?",
    "answers": ["antisepsis", "disinfection", "sterilization", "sanitization"],
    "correct": 2,
    "category": "Infection Control",
    "rationale": "#"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which disinfection/sterilization process is used for processing heat-sensitive items?",
    "answers": ["immersion in a phenolic solution", "immersion in a glutaraldehyde solution", "spraying with a glutaraldehyde solution", "spraying with alcohol"],
    "correct": 1,
    "category": "Infection Control",
    "rationale": "#"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which sterilization process requires pretreatment with a corrosion inhibitor on carbon steel instruments?",
    "answers": ["steam autoclave", "dry heat oven type", "rapid heat transfer", "unsaturated chemical vapor"],
    "correct": 3,
    "category": "Infection Control",
    "rationale": "#"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which sterilization process requires a 270°F (132°C) temperature?",
    "answers": ["dry heat", "unsaturated chemical vapor", "flash or immediate use sterilizer", "steam autoclave"],
    "correct": 3,
    "category": "Infection Control",
    "rationale": "#"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which regulatory agency requires the use of surface disinfection?",
    "answers": ["Food and Drug Administration (FDA)", "Environmental Protection Agency (EPA)", "Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC)", "Occupational Safety and Health Administration (OSHA)"],
    "correct": 3,
    "category": "Infection Control",
    "rationale": "#"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which is a nonregulatory agency that investigates, reports, and tracks specific diseases for public health concerns in the United States?",
    "answers": ["Food and Drug Administration (FDA)", "Environmental Protection Agency (EPA)", "Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC)", "Occupational Safety and Health Administration (OSHA)"],
    "correct": 2,
    "category": "Infection Control",
    "rationale": "#"
  },



  // 71 - 80


  // 81 - 90



// 91 - 100


// finish exam 2
  




];


